<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Caltech Admissions Blog</title>
    <description>Explore life at Caltech!</description>
    <link>caltechadmissions.blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="caltechadmissions.blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 19:31:56 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 19:31:56 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>An Interview with a JPL Mentor!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past several months, I have had the opportunity to intern at the NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL) under the mentorship of senior research technologist Dr. Xiaoqing Pi. Dr. Pi’s guidance and mentorship has been instrumental to the development and success of my internship at JPL, where I use machine-learning to enhance the accuracy and integrity of navigation and communication signals. In addition to helping me develop an understanding of atmospheric and ionospheric remote sensing and machine-learning, Dr. Pi has often offered his insights on how to improve my researching skills. Dr. Pi was generous enough to take the time to answer a few questions regarding his research and advice for future student interns. I believe many students can benefit from some of the lessons that he has taught me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-does-your-research-consist-of&quot;&gt;Q: What does your research consist of?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Xiaoqing Pi:&lt;/strong&gt;  “I have been conducting research on space physics, and remote sensing and modeling of the Earth’s ionosphere. Space physics is a science discipline about physics and systematic interactions between solar wind, interplanetary magnetic field, Earth’s magnetic field, magnetosphere, ionosphere, and thermosphere. The same principles apply to the Sun and other planets, and to other stars and their planets. The ionosphere is the ionized portion of the upper atmosphere at altitudes between about 100 to 1000 kilometers (the layer above 1000 km is called the plasmasphere). It is created by photoionization of the upper atmosphere due to solar EUV radiation. The density, temperature, and velocity of ionospheric charged particles (ions and electrons, or we also call them plasma) vary with solar EUV radiation intensity, the radiation optical path in the atmosphere, atmospheric constituents, and ionospheric dynamics. The ionosphere affects radio signals in ways to delay signals, and sometimes causes random fluctuations in signals, which are called ionospheric scintillation. This occurs if the signals pass through regions of irregularly distributed electron densities or ionospheric irregularities. The signal delay and scintillation effects have an impact on technology systems that rely on radio signals at HF through L-band. Examples include short wave radios, Global Navigation Satellite System (GNSS, including GPS, GLONASS, BeiDou, and Galileo), satellite-based Earth remote sensing radars, etc. Research on space physics helps to advance our understanding of mechanisms of ionospheric variations and disturbances. Development of remote sensing techniques and models helps to augment our observation capability and to enhance the reliability and accuracy of the technology systems”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-do-you-enjoy-the-most-about-your-field-of-study&quot;&gt;Q: What do you enjoy the most about your field of study?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Xiaoqing Pi:&lt;/strong&gt; “What I enjoy the most about my work is that I can pursue scientific discoveries and also conduct development to enhance technology systems. In my study field, I have had chances to conduct research and develop techniques to support satellite-based augmentation system (the Wide Area Augmentation System – WAAS as an example, which is the U.S. system to augment GNSS for aviation navigation), satellite-based interferometric synthetic aperture radars, ocean altimeters, deep space navigation, etc”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q--what-are-some-projects-you-are-currently-working-on&quot;&gt;Q:  What are some projects you are currently working on&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Xiaoqing Pi:&lt;/strong&gt; “I am currently conducting several research projects. One of them is to develop techniques to detect, measure, and remove ionospheric effects globally in satellite-based interferometric synthetic aperture radar imagery. This research supports the upcoming NASA-ISRO SAR mission (NISAR). Another is to analyze scintillation effects on GNSS signals and to develop capability of predicting ionospheric irregularities and scintillation. This research supports the U.S. Wide Area Augmentation System (WAAS). I am also further extending a Global Assimilative Ionospheric Model (GAIM) to estimate ionospheric conditions under which ionospheric irregularities can be triggered. This is a research project under NASA’s Science Mission Directorate Living With a Star (LWS) program”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-how-has-your-experience-been-with-interns-what-do-you-enjoy-about-being-a-mentor&quot;&gt;Q: How has your experience been with interns? What do you enjoy about being a mentor?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Xiaoqing Pi:&lt;/strong&gt; “I have had chances to work with several interns in the past, right now, and in the coming summer at either undergraduate or graduate level. These interns are very excited and enthusiastic about the research projects that they get into. Although the research fields are fresh to them, they are all eager to learn the phenomena, physical processes, and technology, and to contribute to the projects. As their mentor, I am happy to see that they are very motivated to face challenges and pursue solutions in order to reach the research goals”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-advice-do-you-have-for-current-undergraduates-regarding-research-and-internships&quot;&gt;Q: What advice do you have for current undergraduates regarding research and internships?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Xiaoqing Pi:&lt;/strong&gt; “Undergraduate students should not shy away from challenging projects and tasks. They should prepare themselves with required basic skills and by reading relevant references about the research fields. They should follow their mentor’s advice, and actively look for solutions when encountering problems. Take my current research that recruits undergraduate interns through SURF, as an example, the research involves machine learning techniques and Python software. The interested students should be familiar with Python programming skills and familiar with Python-based machine learning libraries as well as their various applications. In addition, students should be prepared to process a large amount of data using Python programs. Different projects require different skills. Interested students may follow mentors’ guidance and suggestions”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q--why-should-students-apply-for-andor-participate-in-nasa-internships&quot;&gt;Q:  Why should students apply for and/or participate in NASA internships?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Xiaoqing Pi:&lt;/strong&gt; “NASA’s research projects are of frontier research. Your mentors are often the front runners of the fields. Being an intern at a NASA center, you will surely learn exciting space science and cutting-edge technologies. Take my current research as an example, one of the major challenges in NASA’s Heliophysics Division research programs is to predict occurrence and intensity of ionospheric irregularities. The irregularities can cause scintillation in trans-ionospheric radio signals, which fades signal power and degrades signal quality. The occurrence and intensity of ionospheric irregularities involve complicated coupling processes between ionized and neutral gas in the upper atmosphere, including their dynamics controlled by the geomagnetic field and impact of solar wind perturbations on the ionosphere and thermosphere. Prediction of the irregularities is needed in certain technology applications, such as satellite-based aviation navigation and radio communications in military operations, as examples. This is an area where machine learning may play a role to solve the problem”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q---what-are-some-qualities-you-look-for-when-selecting-an-intern&quot;&gt;Q:   What are some qualities you look for when selecting an intern?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Xiaoqing Pi:&lt;/strong&gt; “When selecting interns, I look for their enthusiasm about the project, preparedness of the required skills and knowledge about the field, eagerness of learning, good communications, active pursuit of solutions, and team work spirit. In terms of knowledge, one of my research projects requires knowledge of machine learning and its applications, as well as software tools that can be used for machine learning projects. There are some good machine learning libraries written in Python so that Python programming skills are very helpful. In addition, when conducting a specific machine learning task, a large amount of historical data sets is required. With Python programming skills, students can write programs to organize, process and analyze the data and outcome”.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>caltechadmissions.blog/An-Interview-with-a-JPL-Mentor/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">caltechadmissions.blog/An-Interview-with-a-JPL-Mentor/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Forging Ahead with Research while Sheltering in Place</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The transition period to remote learning was a very uncertain time, especially for research and the Caltech Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowships (SURF) program. Many hands-on projects had to pivot at the last minute to facilitate off-campus contributions. However, many Techers were able to take advantage of the research opportunities offered at Caltech and JPL to make the best out of remote learning and research. To paint a picture, I’ve interviewed a few talented Techers for some insight on what researching from home looks like for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-does-your-research-consist-of&quot;&gt;Q: What does your research consist of?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tyrone McNichols, ‘23, CS/Math:&lt;/strong&gt; “I work for the Processors System Development Group at JPL. My work involves developing software for radio astronomy, in particular for NASA’s Deep Space Network”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kristina Stoyanova, ‘23, CS:&lt;/strong&gt; “At the Ron Weiss Mammalian Cell Biology Lab at MIT, I use convolutional neural networks to predict regions of epigenetic marks on DNA sequences. One application of this is to help biologists computationally identify non-functional regions of new genes they’ve created before they even put the DNA into a host organism! The intention is to reduce the trial and error process of research”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anna Li, ‘23, Chemistry:&lt;/strong&gt; “I work on doing molecular dynamics and quantum mechanics calculations on the oxygen evolving complex in Photosystem II as a joint project between the Fischer and Goddard labs. We are working on exploring the mechanisms of photoassembly of the metal cluster, as well as the mechanisms during oxygen evolution”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-does-researching-from-home-look-like-for-you&quot;&gt;Q: What does researching from home look like for you?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tyrone McNichols, ‘23, CS/Math:&lt;/strong&gt; “Mostly remote programming and testing. I also go to a few webex meetings for my group”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kristina Stoyanova, ‘23, CS:&lt;/strong&gt; “Reading papers, planning architectures for the models, and debugging code”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anna Li, ‘23, Chemistry:&lt;/strong&gt; “Well it just looks like me dinking around on my computer in one of Caltech’s clusters”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ug-admissions-caltech-blog-publish.s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/images/2020/12/4th+post.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Interviewees&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-how-do-you-stay-connected-what-programs-facilitate-your-online-research&quot;&gt;Q: How do you stay connected? What programs facilitate your online research?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tyrone McNichols, ‘23, CS/Math:&lt;/strong&gt; “JPL has a slack for employees, and another one specifically for interns which helps a lot. I’m also a part of some employee groups at JPL”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kristina Stoyanova, ‘23, CS:&lt;/strong&gt; “My graduate student mentor Sebastian Palacios, Prof. Ron Weiss, and I have a Slack channel, and we Zoom every week to go over my project’s state”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anna Li, ‘23, Chemistry:&lt;/strong&gt; “I meet with my mentors every week or every other week to go over results. I use NAMD/LAAMPS for molecular dynamics and Jaguar for quantum mechanics”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-any-advice-for-anyone-who-is-or-will-be-researching-from-home&quot;&gt;Q: Any advice for anyone who is or will be researching from home?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tyrone McNichols, ‘23, CS/Math:&lt;/strong&gt; “Make sure you’ve got a consistent work schedule. It’s really easy to get off track online, but separating your life into times when you’re doing work and when you’re not can help a lot”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kristina Stoyanova, ‘23, CS:&lt;/strong&gt; “Even if you want to do laboratory work there is so much prep work (reading papers, training, designing plans for experiments, reading more papers) that could help you hit the ground running once we get back in the lab. Even computational projects can later be verified experimentally. I wish everyone the best of luck with their research!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anna Li, ‘23, Chemistry:&lt;/strong&gt; “Don’t let research become too much stress, classes always come first”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to my peers, my experience, conducting research at JPL remotely, hasn’t been much different from distance learning, structure wise. Luckily, the project I’m involved in is heavily computational, so I am still able to conduct research and contribute to the project remotely. However, just because my internship is online does not mean that the standards at which I need to perform have diminished. It does take a lot of planning and time management to ensure that I stay on track and to reach my research goal in a timely manner. My mentor and I Zoom regularly to discuss updates and results and we share all our work via cloud to make things more accessible. Additionally, my lab has weekly meetings to explore the different research being conducted by members in the lab and catch up with one another. JPL has also been doing a great job at finding creative ways to ensure that interns can continue to learn, conduct research, and feel included. For example, there are multiple informational events and seminars held virtually every week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it’s not ideal to work remotely, and I would have preferred to be on site, obviously no one can control the pandemic. Remote research has been a great learning experience nonetheless and I am thankful for the growth opportunities it’s provided, not only for me but for many other Caltech students as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>caltechadmissions.blog/Research-at-Home/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">caltechadmissions.blog/Research-at-Home/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rotation Rotation Rotation - The Caltech Houses</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My favorite part about Caltech is the Houses! The easiest way to describe them is as Hogwarts houses: each has their own personality and group of people and the first thing you do at Caltech is go through a “sorting” process. The people are what makes the Houses at Caltech so great. As a frosh, it’s amazing to be able to come in and immediately have a group of 100+ people to support you. Because the Houses have students from every grade, you make friends with upperclassmen and can ask for help on tons of things like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hints on difficult problem sets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advice on which classes to take&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to email Professors and find SURFs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What days you should steer clear of House dinners &lt;strong&gt;(mystery fish should remain a mystery)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to find internships and jobs or apply to grad school&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The best restaurants in the Pasadena area&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That one time frosh year you broke your ankle and needed to be driven to physical therapy 3 times a week (thanks Dylan &amp;lt;3)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus the houses also put on tons of social events from a ski trip, beach trip, movie nights, picnics, and tons of secret events you’ll learn about when you join one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I hope your immediate response is: “How do I join these great houses?” This happens through Rotation. Rotation is 2 weeks of House dinners and events so that the prefrosh can get to know all the House cultures. In addition to a dinner and dessert in each House, there are tons of other events from Open Mic Night, Capture the Flag, Grill Night, a House-run Boba Lounge, and many more! Besides getting to know the Houses, all the events are a ton of fun, are a great way to meet other frosh, and almost every single one has food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the 2 weeks of Rotation, you rank the Houses in order of your preference and all the rankings are then fed into an algorithm to match frosh with Houses. Then, the Fleming cannon is fired, all the frosh find out what House they’re in, and they then get rushed off for a night of welcome activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Lloyd House President I had a lot of fun helping to run Rotation and know all the hard work the students put into making it a fun experience for everyone. This year, Rotation has been pushed off to the beginning of Winter term and will be done virtually. With all the time the students are putting into making this new format work, I’m sure it’ll be a great success!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ug-admissions-caltech-blog-publish.s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/images/2020/12/doors.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; doors &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>caltechadmissions.blog/Caltech-Houses/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">caltechadmissions.blog/Caltech-Houses/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Houses</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Indian Festival of Lights</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hey everyone, and happy holidays! Personally, one of my favorite holidays during the season is Diwali. The description you’ll find all over the internet is “Diwali is the Indian Festival of Lights.” This is pretty much what every Diwali-celebrating, South-Asian child in America wrote in their elementary school reports about family traditions during the holidays, but it holds true!  Diwali usually does involve lighting candles and sparklers, and generally celebrates the triumph of good over evil in various mythologies. I like to think of it as a time of general goodwill and festivity. In non-pandemic times, Diwali celebrations might include with boisterous parties with tons of people and desserts and music. Last year, a couple of my friends and I organized an event in Ruddock House for people to come celebrate, complete with sweets and sparklers! However, the 2020 version, like for most things, has had to be toned down. We got together over Zoom instead, and although it couldn’t fully match the vibe of being in person, the spirit was definitely there. And, it’s nice to think that we’ve started a yearly tradition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festivity (and Bollywood music) also makes me miss Dhamaka, the Bollywood dance team we have on campus. I joined Dhamaka during my freshman year: it all started out as me tagging along with friends who had pushed me to go with them to the first practice. I was pretty apprehensive because I had never really been on an official dance team before, or ever danced on a stage for that matter, but the group was incredibly welcoming! It didn’t matter that I didn’t have previous experience (as is the case for many clubs on campus!), and it was a fun outlet for me to take a break from sets every weekend. We would meet every week or so to practice for the Caltech Dance Show, held in the spring every year, where we were the big finale! Check us out on YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FeR7GkrP-0Y&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ug-admissions-caltech-blog-publish.s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/images/2020/12/dhamaka_promo.JPG&quot; alt=&quot; Dhamaka &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, Dhamaka also paired with OASIS (Organization of the Associated Students of the Indian Subcontinent), a grad student-led cultural club on campus, to put on a Holi event! Holi is another festival celebrated in India, during which people welcome the season of spring with lots of color. I celebrated Holi with family and friends every year without fail before coming to Caltech, so it was rewarding to be able to share the experience with my college friends for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ug-admissions-caltech-blog-publish.s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/images/2020/12/holi_group.JPG&quot; alt=&quot; Holi &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also performed at this event with Dhamaka right before everyone had to leave campus in March. I suppose it was sort of our last hurrah for the year, but I’m looking forward to continuing all these traditions and events next year and am glad to be part of a community that is full of culture!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>caltechadmissions.blog/The-Indian-Festival-of-Lights/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">caltechadmissions.blog/The-Indian-Festival-of-Lights/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflecting on College Admissions</title>
        <description>&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-do-you-remember-feeling-when-you-found-out-you-had-been-accepted-to-caltech&quot;&gt;What do you remember feeling when you found out you had been accepted to Caltech?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: I was completely shocked. Caltech had been my first-choice school for years (warm weather, great science, what’s not to love?). However, I didn’t ever think I’d get in: nobody had gotten in from my high school in the living memory of any teacher and my guidance counselor had told me point blank that it was a longshot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the scene: December 15, 2016. A cold, chilly day in Denver, Colorado. I’m wearing a sports coat and khaki pants. Why? Well, I was in the literal middle of an interview with Duke when I got the email push notification saying that there was an update to my admissions portal. To this day I have absolutely no idea how I finished that interview. But once I got out of eyesight, I immediately opened my phone and clicked on the link expecting to find disappointment. I was amazed to be greeted with confetti instead – so much so that I did a jump and punched the air, much to the confusion of the few people walking on the street beside me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-did-you-decide-to-attend-caltech&quot;&gt;How did you decide to attend Caltech?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, it came down 100% to academics. When I visited Caltech on a tour, one of the fencing team members had told me that Caltech Geological and Planetary Sciences was objectively and subjectively the best undergraduate program in the world. And honestly that’s true. It’s a 2:1 faculty to student ratio, and we get a trip to Hawaii senior year (although maybe not this year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://blueberry-elephant.s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/amchan/12_17/Ge+11a+Field+Trip.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;A Fieldtrip to Death Valley&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What really sold it was the interactions I had on my visit to campus. One of the professors, Paul Asimow, spent an hour showing me every geosciences lab and talking about the research. It’s this connection that immediately made me realize the potential of Caltech. A tenured faculty member was taking time to interact with me, a student who hadn’t even committed yet. I’ll talk about this more in another post, but I really didn’t relate to any of the students I met (although I’ve since met great people on campus). But when I committed, I was willing to completely sacrifice my social life for four years to get that student-faculty relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-do-you-wish-you-could-go-back-and-tell-yourself-senior-year-of-high-school&quot;&gt;What do you wish you could go back and tell yourself senior year of high school?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would’ve told myself to relax a bit. Have fun. Enjoy the people I was around and the memories I was making. I haven’t really interacted with a lot of people from high school since graduating. Most of them have stayed in-state with the same friend groups they’ve always had. I think one thing I didn’t really do is appreciate those connections enough in the moment. High school isn’t really a fun time, and we all suffered through that together. I wish I’d spent more time with those people and really just cherished that bond – I didn’t really realize how special that was until it was gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-advice-would-you-give-to-the-admitted-class-of-2025&quot;&gt;What advice would you give to the admitted Class of 2025?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to spin this out in a separate post, but in short, it’s this: take the time to know every school you get accepted to. Make sure that above parental influence, external pressure, or scary posts on Quora, you make the best choice for yourself. Whether that’s Caltech or anywhere else. Our school isn’t right for everyone. But if you were admitted, our admissions team believes that it’s right for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Chandrew&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>caltechadmissions.blog/Reflecting-On-College-Admissions/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">caltechadmissions.blog/Reflecting-On-College-Admissions/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My Best Advice for the Class of 2025</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s crazy to think that it has been four years now since I was applying to college. I remember it vividly. This week we’re spending some time reflecting on our personal admissions processes, and how we ended up at Caltech. There’s one question though that I wanted to spin out into a separate post: “what advice would you give to the admitted class of 2025?” And I think the best way to do this is to tell a more detailed story than I did in my other post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I almost didn’t come to Caltech.&lt;/strong&gt; I was extremely fortunate during college admissions: I got into 6/7 schools I applied to, all them very competitive schools. My decision came down to this: Caltech, a half tuition scholarship at one school (13% acceptance), tiny scholarship at another school (9% acceptance). Honestly, it really came down to Caltech and the last school – their admissions officer had handwritten me a note about my application with specific comments on my essay, and honestly, I just felt wanted there. Caltech was objectively the better school academically (especially in the geosciences), but I really did not connect with the people when I visited. In-fact, I actually really didn’t like a single person I met while touring Caltech. Because of the house system on campus people with certain hobbies/interests often group together at Tech and during my Caltech in a day experience I didn’t interact with a single person from the house I ended up in, or any of the houses that I share interests with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it came down to was this: I was going to go out to participate in the other school’s weekend event, but it conflicted with the FIRST Robotics World Championships, so I didn’t go. I know for a fact that if I had gone to that school’s weekend event that I would not have attended Caltech, and that that would have likely been the biggest mistake of my life. In this particular circumstance, fate, or perhaps the butterfly effect, intervened and led to me committing to Caltech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, here’s my conclusion. My advice for you, whether it’s at Caltech, or any school you go to, is to make sure you know the complete picture before deciding. Know the school, make the time to visit (perhaps virtually this year), and meet some students. That way, no matter what you end up picking, you’ll know that you’ve made the best choice for you and for your future. I’ll be honest, Caltech is not easy. I’ve been working harder and had much less fun than most of my other friends in college. And I’d do it all again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Chandrew&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>caltechadmissions.blog/My-Best-Advice-for-the-Class-of-2025/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">caltechadmissions.blog/My-Best-Advice-for-the-Class-of-2025/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Admissions Reflections</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-do-you-remember-feeling-when-you-found-out-you-had-been-accepted-to-caltech&quot;&gt;What do you remember feeling when you found out you had been accepted to Caltech?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember the exact moments I got into Caltech. I was backstage at a dance recital, I had my hair and makeup done, I was in costume and about 20 minutes away from going on stage to perform. I had to quickly run upstairs to forward my mom the email link with the recital tickets since there was no signal backstage. After I forwarded her the email, I noticed an email from Caltech with a subject line of “View your Caltech admissions decision online.” To be perfectly honest, I thought there was no way I would get in. I had resolved myself to opening the rejection and moving on with my day. I logged into my account and opened the letter. Confetti flew across my screen as I read the words “Congratulations!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I screamed in excitement and ran backstage. I screamed at my best friend Mary: “I GOT INTO CALTECH!” I was beyond excited and frankly completely in shock. Tears of joy filled my eyes, and it took all the self-control in the world to not completely ruin my stage makeup. I went on stage about 5 minutes later and the show was a disaster. I forgot all the choreography and was consistently a beat behind the other dancers, but that still did not put a damper on my mood. I was simply too ecstatic to even care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-did-you-decide-to-attend-caltech&quot;&gt;How did you decide to attend Caltech?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, Caltech was the best school I got into so the decision was not difficult. I was concerned that I would not fit in because I expected everyone to be the same “cookie-cutter” nerd that wanted to study 24/7. While I love science, I also wanted to have a social life in college, make friends, and have interests beyond academics. After visiting campus, I realized, yes, everyone is a huge science nerd (in the best possible way). But, everyone had their own passions and interests that they wanted to pursue. The experience made me realize Caltech is more than just “an academically rigorous” university, it is also a community that I would find my place in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expected everyone at Caltech to be the same person: a workaholic science geek that only wanted to study and do research all the time. This intimidated me because I also wanted to find friends and have a social life outside of school. I visited Caltech and talked to current students to see if Caltech was the right fit. After my visit, I realized Caltech is full of diverse personalities and interests and I would be able to find my people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-do-you-wish-you-could-go-back-and-tell-yourself-senior-year-of-high-school&quot;&gt;What do you wish you could go back and tell yourself senior year of high school?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would tell myself to learn more basic life skills -namely, personal finance, organization, time management, and cooking. Although I am pretty good at these things now, I think my life in college would have been easier if I learned these things during high school instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-advice-would-you-give-to-the-admitted-class-of-2025&quot;&gt;What advice would you give to the admitted Class of 2025?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caltech is full of resources and it is important to take advantage of them. However, take other people’s advice with a grain of salt. You must decide what YOU want out of life and out of college. For example, upperclassmen are a great resource. They can tell you if your course load is too ambitious, or which classes are fun to take, etc. But at the end of the day, you know yourself the best. When I was a freshman, I gave too much credence to upperclassmen opinions. I decided to try out computer science because so many people advocated for the major and the career. However, I knew that I was more passionate about biology and chemistry. Now, I am a Premed pursuing a chemistry degree.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>caltechadmissions.blog/admissions-reflections/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">caltechadmissions.blog/admissions-reflections/</guid>
        
        
        <category>acceptance</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>In Search of Element 79</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s a familiar story told by a select few. I anticipated the first line to read, “We regret to inform you.” Instead, orange and silver confetti fluttered across my laptop screen. My acceptance filled me with joy and disbelief. After telling the good news to friends, family, and mentors, I realized how much I sacrificed for this outcome. The sum of all my opportunity costs–the weekends preparing for science competitions, late nights crossing fruit flies, and weeks tweaking my essays instead of having more typical teenage adventures–cashed in at this one point in time. My high school experience could’ve been different, but I don’t regret my choices. I had so much fun learning and researching that I wanted to, in earnest, do more of that in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Years spent scaling the stucco wall left little time to imagine what’s on the other side. Maybe it’s a form of self-protection, but during the application process I didn’t think much about what it meant to “be a Caltech student.” The fear of getting my hopes up came second to the fear of losing myself in prestigiousness. As cheesy as it sounds, when I did dream of what I’d do in college, I imagined dramatically scribbling equations on blackboards or commanding a fleet of drones from my dorm room. I didn’t need to go to Caltech to do those things, but it would be the best place where I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the wall, I wondered if I should commit. I’d likely lose touch with my friends and family. Unsure of my future, I looked to the past for guidance–to the 19th-century pioneers headed west in search of gold. With a clear purpose, they were able to survive the arduous journey. They shouldered being lost, sick, and ambushed in the hope their efforts would pay off someday. Similar in spirit and destination, I decided to attend Caltech because my mission has remained singular: I want to learn science and engineering from the best in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visiting Caltech gave me greater confidence in my decision. Its sunkissed campus, unparalleled research, and tight-knit community captivated me. Although Tech has been unforgiving at times, it has kept its promise in supporting my mission. In my first year, I saw the fly brain glow in response to an odor. I watched Einstein’s equations of special relativity leap out from Maxwell’s equations. I expressed the closed-form of the Fibonacci sequence using the golden ratio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having completed two years, I have my short stack of shiny ingots. There is still so much to discover. To those starting this journey, I offer you the same golden nugget I found in Feynman’s &lt;em&gt;Perfectly Reasonable Deviations from the Beaten Track&lt;/em&gt;: Study hard what interests you the most in the most undisciplined, irreverent, and original manner possible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>caltechadmissions.blog/In-Search-of-Element-79/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">caltechadmissions.blog/In-Search-of-Element-79/</guid>
        
        
        <category>acceptance</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Online School.. on Mars</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When the announcement was first made that fall term was going to be online, I started talking to friends and looking for places to live. We were debating locations around the country: California, Florida, New York, etc.. there were plenty of options. Then it suddenly hit me, what is stopping us from going to Hawaii, covid numbers were better and a two week quarentine would ensure that numbers stayed down… I proposed this to my friend and we agreed it would be an amazing experience, but we didn’t want to get out hopes up. A month or so later we still haven’t decided where to live, Hawaii seemed too far and too difficult to plan. But we couldn’t get the idea out of our heads. We spent some time looking into plane tickets, places to stay, etc… and it actually didn’t seem so impossible after all. A couple weeks later and we were arriving here on the big island!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So online school is of course not really on Mars, but I thought that picture looked a lot like it! That photo is actually from the world’s tallest mountain: Mauna Kea. Yes, Mauna Kea is the world’s &lt;em&gt;tallest&lt;/em&gt; mountain, Everest is the world’s &lt;em&gt;highest&lt;/em&gt; mountain. Everest is 29032 feet above sea level while Mauna Kea is only 13803 feet above sea level, however Mauna Kea from bottom to peak is over 32800 feet tall (compared to Everest’s 29000 feet from bottom to peak). With school being online, a couple of my friends and I packed our bags and moved to Hawaii for fall term!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explored caves created by flowing lava!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ug-admissions-caltech-blog-publish.s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/images/2020/11/cave.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cave&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seen some pretty amazing waterfalls!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ug-admissions-caltech-blog-publish.s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/images/2020/11/waterfall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;waterfall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swam with huge (8 foot+) manta rays!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ug-admissions-caltech-blog-publish.s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/images/2020/11/mantas.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;mantas&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And more! Overall, I have had an amazing experience here in Hawaii.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I miss Caltech dearly, this opportunity to go explore Hawaii with my friends is an unforgettable and amazing experience!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the decision to come to Hawaii was a very sudden and spur of the moment choice, something I usually don’t do! Yet this has become one of the most amazing experiences of my life! Have you experienced any “good accidents”? Let me know in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>caltechadmissions.blog/Online-School-on-Mars/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">caltechadmissions.blog/Online-School-on-Mars/</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>AnnABEL&apos;s Theorem</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever gotten lost trying to find an address? Have you ever been annoyed by the voice on your phone telling you to “Turn left in 100 ft.” when in reality there is no street to turn into? When you find an address using your phone, have you ever wondered where that information comes from? I think we all have. GPS (Global Positioning System) is a system composed of a fleet of about 24 satellites put into orbit and maintained by the U.S. Department of defense. This technology is used to find a position on Earth by using a mathematical technique, called trilateration. Trilateration uses about 3 satellites, at any given time, to determine an object’s speed, elevation, and position. Most electronic devices come with a built-in GPS chip and use Wi-Fi networks and cellphone towers to enhance location accuracy and calculate its position. Even though GPS is a highly sophisticated system, it is far from perfect! It is not uncommon for it to malfunction when a navigator cannot receive sufficient satellite data or when signals move too slowly due to atmospheric irregularities in the troposphere and ionosphere. This, in turn, can output inaccuracies in location calculations which can cause serious problems in navigation and aviation in addition to unnecessary stress and frustration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ug-admissions-caltech-blog-publish.s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/images/2020/11/D86F6843-AD65-45E9-A5B5-FDA349117BC7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;GPS&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are multiple ways to refine GPS functionality. One of these ways is to improve its accuracy. Over the last several months, I have been conducting research at the NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL), under the mentorship of JPL senior research technologist Dr. Xiaoqing Pi. Our research involves using machine-learning to increase the integrity of navigation and communication signals. More specifically, we work on studying and predicting ionospheric irregularities triggered by geomagnetic storms, plasma convection, and associate dynamics in the high-latitude ionosphere. Our goal is to reduce signal reception interruptions, caused by solar activity such as solar flares and coronal mass ejections. We aim to increase the accuracy of technology applications that rely on the Global Navigation Satellite System and GPS data. My individual contributions include developing and applying Python-based machine learning to improve navigation and communication signal integrity. I am responsible for downloading, analyzing, and processing various sets of GPS and magnetometer data using Python programs, which I write from scratch. Once the data is pre-processed, I run it through several machine-learning algorithms that I’ve developed, to predict the time, location, and intensity of these ionospheric irregularities. After the predictions are generated, I analyze their accuracy by calculating their correlations against historical data. The goal is for these algorithms, once implemented, to accurately predict ionospheric irregularities, under various geophysical and space weather conditions, in real time, reducing the impact of ionospheric scintillation on receptions of GNSS signals and data; thus improving navigation systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this research continues to evolve and the accuracy of these predictions increases, GPS malfunctions could potentially be a problem of the past! Devices and technology could be engineered to take the above predictions into account and adapt their outputs accordingly, making them more accurate and reliable. Hopefully, next time you use GPS to find directions to the nearest boba shop, you’ll get there on a timely manner and without getting lost!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ug-admissions-caltech-blog-publish.s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/images/2020/11/BFD51676-1FAF-4351-88ED-3BEC7AD278C7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Directions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>caltechadmissions.blog/Annabels-Theorem/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">caltechadmissions.blog/Annabels-Theorem/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
